

#### DATA ENGINEER II

Uluberia, Howrah -711316

□ (+91) 7003190619 | Soumitra.banerjee@hotmail.com | Soumitrabanerjee.qithub.io/ | Soumitra-banerjee

# Summary .

Current Big Data Engineer at American Express with 2.2+ years of professional experience specializing in development and deployment of big data components via Spark, Hadoop, Hive, Scala technologies. Excellent planning skills in setting and achieving goals, including meeting tight deadlines. Interested in devising a better problem-solving method for challenging tasks, and learning new technologies and tools if the need arises.

# **Experience**

American Express Bangalore, India

DATA ENGINEER II

Sep. 2022 - Present

- Working with vPayment team to modify data type and receive at our end by changing and applying new methodologies through scala-spark.
- · Worked on production defects and fixing exiting code.

#### **Cognizant Technology Solutions India Pvt Ltd**

Pune, India

PROGRAMMER ANALYST (DATA ENGINEER)

Sep. 2020 - Sep. 2022

- Developed scala code to receive data in json format from REST API and applied filter conditions to convert it into table data.
- Developed code from scratch to convert views objects to any file format in Scala to integrate it with the project.
- Developed code from scratch to keep track of the running jobs, archive table records and maintain history tables and update the job status in data base object.
- · Built a Java program to help solve internal problem for comparing data from different environments (Dev, QA and Prod).
- Working on API Gateway based data source for revamping the business logic for user operation on PRTS data from upstream system to Landing layer using Scala code.
- · Worked on Bug Fixing on Spark SQL scripts.
- Worked on Reverse Engineering by backtracking the Database objects from Downstream Systems till Upstream Systems to ensure proper data flow between different layers of the systems.

#### **Cognizant Technology Solutions India Pvt Ltd**

Kolkata, India

Intern Jan. 2020 - Apr. 2020

• Trained on Data Warehouse Under Cognizant Trainers' supervision and learnt SQL, Databases, Core-JAVA, OLAP Concept.

• Built a small OOPs based java application to store books details.

### Skills\_

**Big Data Tools** Databricks, Hadoop, Spark, Hive, Airflow

**Programming** Experienced: Java, Scala, SQL | Familiar: Python

**Languages** Fluent: English, Hindi, Bengali

#### Education

#### University of Engineering and Management, Kolkata

Kolkata,India

B.Tech in Computer Science and Engineering

Jul. 2016 - Jun. 2020

• Graduated with a DGPA of 8.95

#### Sri Chaitanya Techno School(CBSE)

Visakhapatnam,India

HIGHER SECONDARY (10 + 2)

2016

Passed with overall aggregate 76.20%
CMCL Vidya Bharati School(CBSE)

Meghalaya,India

SECONDARY

2014

• Passed with overall aggregate 85.50%

## **Certifications**

#### **Scala Programming**

Online

• Learned Scala and its implementation through spark. certificate no.: UC-05ab48e9-40b1-444f-abb1-3706232066ff

DECEMBER 13, 2022

SOUMITRA BANERJEE · CURRICULUM VITAE

AWS Concepts Online

UDEMY

• Learned basics of AWS Cloud and its components. certificate no.: UC-b4555cb2-2b33-4298-9fd3-8edef3289c48

# Extracurricular Activity \_\_\_\_\_

- · Received "Working as One" award from Cognizant upon successful completion and smooth delivery of previous project.
- Built small projects in college on web application using HTML, PHP, MySQL, CSS.
- Participated in North-East regional science exhibiton held in Guwahati.
- Gained expertise in testing, especially targeted on big data application and business features.
- Participated in India's largest canvas painting held in Guwahati.

Feb. 9 2020